Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) PE.017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME)
1937-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.017
2 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. AFSCME was founded in 1932 in Wisconsin as an organization of white collar workers who wanted to save the civil service system in their state. The organization quickly spread to the national level. The material in the collection ranges in date from 1937 to the present and is generated by the national and international bodies of the union as well as from a few of its District Councils and Locals, notably District Council 1707, the Community and Social Agency Employees. The collection is made up of contracts, agreements and constitutions as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
AFSCME was founded in 1932 in Wisconsin as an organization of white collar workers who wanted to save the civil service system in their state. The organization quickly spread to the national level. By 1936, the American Federation of Labor had granted a charter to AFSCME. At the time, the union was 10,000 members strong, but with the integration of the AFL and the CIO in 1955, AFSCME accommodated 40,000 more members. The composition also began to change to include more blue collar workers, who were more familiar with trade unions and trade union organizing. During the 1960s, AFSCME was involved in the civil rights and student movements, culminating in a strike of sanitary workers in Memphis, Tennessee attempting to gain union recognition after two African American men were crushed to death in a garbage truck.
Jerry Wurf served as president from 1964-1981. Under his leadership, AFSCME drew up a new international constitution which included a member bill of rights, the first of its kind in union history. AFSCME's primary focus was on winning collective bargaining laws, and was successful in gaining an increase in wages and family health insurance benefits through collective bargaining agreements with dozens of states.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME) gives a broad and general sense of the type of printed material generated by the national and international bodies of the union as well as the District Councils and Locals. The collection is made up largely of agreements, contracts and constitutions as well as fliers, pamphlets and publications. The pamphlets and publications are on a range of subjects, including sexual harassment and pay equity. There are also several manuals for stewards. A small amount of material documents activities of various rank and file groups including the Penn AFSCME Organizing Committee out of the University of Pennsylvania. The material in the collection ranges in date from 1937 to the present.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 1707 (WAG 298)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), District Council 37 (WAG 265)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 0420 (Hospital Workers) Photographs (PHOTOS 212)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 0420 (Hospital Workers) Records (WAG 215)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 1306 Records (WAG 290)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 1930, New York Public Library Guild Photographs (PHOTOS 17)
American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, District Council 37, Local 1930, New York Public Library Guild, Records (WAG 040)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
Printed ephemera.; Clippings (information artifacts); Publications (documents); Press releases.; Labor unions -- New York (State); Pamphlets.; Constitutions.; Circular letters.; Fliers (printed matter); Agreements.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor unions; Reports.; AFSCME; AFSCME. District Council 1707
- Association of Workers in Public Relief Agencies, 1937 (Box 1)
- Biographical Information, 1975-1976, 1995 (Box 1)
- Circular Letters, 1943, 1975-1983, 2001, undated (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1940-1965 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1970-1978 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1980-1988 (Box 1)
- Constitutions, 1990-1998 (Box 1)
- Council 13 (Pennsylvania), 1992 (Box 1)
- Council 93 (Massachusetts Public Employees), 1983 (Box 1)
- Department of Public Policy Analysis, 1977 (Box 1)
- District Council 33 (Philadelphia, PA), undated (Box 1)
- District Council 57 (California), 1995 (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY), undated (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY), 1950-1959 (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY), 1961-1988 (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY): Agreements and Contracts, 1957, 1960, undated (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY): Build the Union Committee, 1971, undated (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY): By-laws and Constitutions, 1958, undated (Box 1)
- District Council 1707 (Community and Social Agency Employees, New York, NY): Committee to Reform the Union, 1961-1962, undated (Box 1)
- Education Department/Division of Education, 1944, 1958, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
- Fliers and Ephemera, circa 1940s-2000, undated (Box 1)
- International Conventions, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
- International Conventions, 1970 (Box 1)
- International Conventions, 1988-1994 (Box 1)
- International Conventions, 2000 (Box 1)
- Jerry Wurf Memorial Fund, undated (Box 1)
- Local 26, 1983 (Box 2)
- Local 124, 1956 (Box 2)
- Local 207 (Detroit, MI), 2006 (Box 2)
- Local 1000 (Civil Service Employees Association, Albany, NY), undated (Box 2)
- Local 1000 (Civil Service Employees Association, Albany, NY), 1977-1989, 2010- (Box 2)
- Local 1000 (Civil Service Employees Association, Albany, NY): Agreements, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
- Local 1000 (Civil Service Employees Association, Albany, NY): Agreements, 1988-1995 (Box 2)
- Local 1037, 1975 (Box 2)
- Local 1583, 1977 (Box 2)
- Local 2093, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
- Local 2298 (Newark, NJ), 1974, 1988 (Box 2)
- Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1975, undated (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1958, 1969 (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1978-1984 (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications, 1991-1999 (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications: Pay Equity, 1980-1985, undated (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications: Sexual Harassment, 1981-1988, undated (Box 2)
- Pamphlets and Publications: Steward's Handbooks and Manuals, undated (Box 2)
- Penn AFSCME Organizing Committee, 1975-1976, undated (Box 2)
- Press Releases, 1964, undated (Box 2)
- Rank and File News, 1968 (Box 2)
- Reports, 1953, 1969 (Box 2)
- Research Department, 1982-1988 (Box 2)
- Statements, undated (Box 2)